Hi today we'll be looking at the radial basis function. Basically what the radial basis function
is is a way to interpolate your data when you have sparse data and you want to have a smooth
interpretation between those. Let's see how it is done mathematically because it will be used
in several papers when we try to analyze them. So the first thing I will do is again import all
all the libraries I would need,
so I will be able to display what I'm doing.
And why do we call that radial basis functions?
It's basically because we have a function
that only depends on the distance between
the point I'm trying to interpolate
and all the points I have inside of my data.
So I will have examples, a bunch of examples,
and I try to interpolate in betweens.
And the only thing that I'm interested in
is the distance between the point I have
and all my examples to try to find the interpolated values.
So that's why we said that it's a radial functions.
And it's only depending on the distance.
So the points I'm looking at
compared to all the points I have.
And then we will go through a kernel.
So instead of just having the linear distance,
you could pass that through any type of function.
There is a lot of different kernels.
And one of the most used is the Gaussian kernel
that I would call phi in this case.
And the Gaussian is basically the exponential of minus epsilon
r squared r being the distance itself.
And epsilon is how much I want to make that bell curve short
or big.
Before going through all the maths,
I will just show you basically what I'm talking about.
So I get the Gaussian, so that's the ghost,
see the exponential functions as we have here.
And I will basically call one example function,
so I would know what are the functions
and I will just pick a few points around that function
and I will display the function.
So basically, what I have is this.
And I have a ground truth, and the ground truth
is my red dots.
And then I get a bunch of points that I have,
for which I have the values.
So that would be the points I would have truly measured
something in the real world.
And I need to be able to interpolate, basically,
to re-draw that red curve without knowing what was the function before, just by knowing
the points I have here.
So that's the point of the radial basis functions interpolations.
And how we will do this, as I said, it's going through the Gaussians.
Basically the function is here, so the function to find any x value will be the sum of all
the distances I will have between my points and all the examples I have multiplied by
weights. And then we'll have to do some stuff. So let's see what happens if I just try to
do that sum. So to represent what I have here, I've kept all the points that I had in my
function. So that's all the points I had here. I have all those points. And then I will draw
one Gaussian through each of the points so you can see that I get the blue one
right there it's at the bottom then the second one is that yellow and you get the
bell curve you know that goes here with the the correct points and then the
green one the red one and the purple one and what we do is that we sum all of
them to try to find the approximation the interpretation we want and if I
sum all of those of course what I have is this big function that's completely
over shooting what I'm trying to interpolate. And what I could do is I can change the Gaussian
curve itself to make it really a small bell curve. And so the approximation, the interpolation
here is closer, it doesn't add to be that big, but then you know that now we dip around
here we go down which is not what we want. So depending on the value of the Gaussian you have
you get an interpolation that is really smooth or really precise but tends to go down and not
working properly. So the purpose of the radial basis functions now is to actually
solve this, so the interpolation will go through all the points. And to do this, what
we have, that I haven't used yet, is to say that we had a weight that we could use for
each point. So basically, for the first point I have one weight, for the second point I
have a second weight, third weight, fourth weight and fifth weight. So I get a weight
for each of those so I can add them together but multiply them by the weights and now we
have to find the weights that make sure that we will go through all the points.
And how to do this, basically what we do is that we will turn this into a system of equation
because what we could say is that I know that for my first point, for instance, so if I
I go 0.1 minus 0.1, I know the value where it would be.
So I know that that would be the value 1.
And for my 0.2 minus 0.2, it has to be at the value of 0.2,
and so on and so on.
So I know what the weight should be for each of the points
that I know.
So basically what I would do is just this.
I will compute the distance between every point,
so between all the points i minus all the points j.
So basically, I do for every point,
I do the weights for every point.
And that gives me a system of equations.
So I get the first point minus the first point,
the first point minus the second point, and so on, and so on.
Multiply by the first weight, and so on, and so on.
That gives me my first value.
And that's the known values I have.
So because it's a system of equation,
now that it's actually a squared matrices here,
I can just solve this.
I can solve for w and I would know the w I want to use.
So let's see how we do this.
I will force my epsilon to be two.
So basically like this fairly smooth.
So I really force it to be two and then I compute my distance and as I said is
between each point and each point and the way I'm doing it is just subtracting
all the points but then I'm taking the advantage of the broadcast of NumPy to
make sure that it will build a big matrices with all the distance between
between all the points.
So compute all the distance,
and then I will just make those distances
go through my Gaussian functions
because that's the kernel I want to use,
and that will give me my phi.
So first is all the distance.
So of course you could see in the diagonal,
the distance is zero because that's the point one
with the point one, the point two with point two
and so on and so on.
And then it's a big symmetric matrix.
But basically, you get the distance between 0.1 and 2,
0.1 and 3, and so on and so on.
And then when I go through the Gaussian,
now what I have is the value when
I go through the Gaussians.
And now, of course, in diagonal, I
get 1's because at 0.1, I want to be at 0.1.
At 0.2, I want to be at 0.2.
At 0.3, I want to be at 0.3.
and so on and I get the different sums of all the weights I want to use and now as I
said I get so that's really here that's this matrix and now I can solve for my weights
if I solve my weights, that's the values of all my weights now. So that's the weights for each of my
points. So I can use the function we had. Remember just the sum of all the distances
multiplied by the weights. What I will do is that instead of writing this as a sum,
I will write this as a matrix multiplication. It's exactly the same stuff. I'm multiplying
my points minus 0.1 with the weight 1, my points minus 0.2 with the weight 2 and so on and so on.
And if I do this basically what I have is that I compute the distance now I will pick randomly
the value 0.5 so that's the on the x-axis I want to know the value of 0.5 so I can 0.5
minus all my all my points. I can make that go through the Gaussian and then I
can do the multiplication, the matrix multiplication to get the values I will
have. I haven't displayed it yet but so that's the value for the point zero five
and the reason why I wrote this as a matrix form and not as a sum, it's
It's because, as usual, inside of NumPy,
I can compute more than one thing at once.
So what I would do is that,
instead of computing only one values
and having only one row here,
I can have as many rows as I want
and that gives me as many answer as I want.
So what I could do is I could actually
compute the distance between all the points I want to do
to draw my curves at once and get all the values
and that's what I do here.
And now it's time for me to display this.
And what I will have is again the red is the ground truth
and the green is the interpolated value.
So you could see the interpolation is fairly close.
And one thing that we have with radial basis functions
by default is that it's really good at interpolation.
it's really bad at extrapolation
because it has no clue that it should be going up here.
There's no data for him to know
that it should be going up and so on.
So really good interpolation, really bad at extrapolation.
They could see, so then my green curve
and then the values I've computed for the 0.5 is just here.
It's right on the green curve, of course.
And that's basically what you do
When you hear about radial basis function interpolation,
that's it.
That's how you compute it.
Of course, your weights can be in multidimensional.
It doesn't need to be just, like in this case, one dimension.
But it's the same principle.
Another thing that I wanted to talk about
is the polynomial augmentation.
because sometime here I get something fairly smooth
and we could guess already just by seeing
where the curve would be.
So it's really good interpolating this kind of stuff.
But then I can easily find a function
that will not have a proper Gaussian
and radial basis function interpolation.
What I had is, I wrote a different example.
And I've picked a bunch of points on that functions.
And then what I've done is all the step we had before,
I computed the distance solve for my w's
and then try to interpolate using my weights.
And you could see that what I have is that red interpolation
and it just dips to zero.
There is no way for him to do the interpolation
because the data is way too sparse
and it's missing information, let's say,
to be able to do a proper interpolation.
What I can see visually here and I could guess,
and I actually mainly know because of the function I wrote,
is this is probably a quadratic.
And I can actually try to tell the interpolation
that on top of all my Gaussians, I
want him to make sure that he tries
to find a quadratic function to do that interpolation.
So that's what we could do, and we
could grow the system that we had before with just
the matrix of phi and weights.
Grow it with a bunch of constraints,
and those constraints will be tried to find a polynomial.
And to do this, what we do is that we
add a second term to the functions,
and the second term is to say that we
have a polynomial basis and a bunch of coefficients
for those polynomials.
Then I could choose the type of polynomial I'm trying to solve,
because what I can see here that it's probably
quadratic and I know it's a quadratic I will tell him as a constraint I want you
to find a quadratic polynomial so I will build a bunch of polynomial basis of
degree 2 which gives me this matrix so basically what it says it says that I
have a matrix with first row is always 1 and then I get the values for x and
and then I get the value for x squared so I will have minus 2 and then 4
then I do a second row it will be for x2
which is a bit bigger, I don't remember what the values are but
you see it will be also minus 150 and then
squared and so on and so on so you do it for as many degrees you have and for
all the x's you have
so basically what I have in my case is this P
I get, from all the points I had here, minus 2, minus 1.8, minus 1.7, 1.802, then it turns
into this matrix and then it's 1, minus 2, 4, 1, minus 1.8, 3, 24, and so on and so on.
So that's the P I would have.
Now how do you combine the phi and the polynomial?
You turn it into a matrix form that
contains all those constraints.
And how you do it is basically you
will make a matrix that is a bit bigger.
And at the top corner, you get the same matrix
as the one we had before.
Then next to it, we put all the matrix for the P's.
Under the other one, we put the transpose
of all the matrix for the P's,
and then everything else stays just a bunch of zeros.
So that matrix, it's written as a matrix,
but really this one is a matrix,
that one is a matrix and so on.
So you have to make in your head
that it's just a matrix that is bigger.
And then where we had just the weights, now we have the weights and then we have the coefficients we want to find for the polynomials.
So basically what it means, it means that for all of the values I have here, all the different values,
I will try to find for all the x and x, for all the ones, the x and the x squares,
I will try to find the same coefficients because they're the only ones, so I will need to find
the coefficients for all the different polynomials that make sure that this looks like a polynomial.
And on the solutions there, we have the f, so the values we know, and then under it a
bunch of zeros because basically we want to solve for a plus bx plus cx squared equals
zeroes. That's what you try to do. So we solve for the vector w and c. Let's do it this.
So I get my extended phi now. So basically see it the same. I started with the distance
and the Gaussian, and then I created a new matrix that is bigger with a much of zeroes
and I've just injected in the right corners the data for phi, p and p transpose.
And now I can do, I can solve the w's. So I get a bunch of w's here. And what you do is that if
I reuse that same concept now to interpolate, so for each values I want to look and also build
the extended phi and interpolates using the extended phi then I only take the values that
I'm interested no so not all the zeros I will have at the end only the the extended values
what I have is this interpolations and then if I render I get this so that's interpolations if it
find. So it did find a perfect polynomial to interpolate the points I have here.
That's in the theory, that's what I wanted to show you, how you do it before starting to
make things a bit more messy. Because what you've done here is basically
actually did a little. What happened is that I've created a perfect function, I've sampled
that function, and I gave that function to the system. What happened really if you check
the values that this one prints, it's a bit maybe abstract to read, but basically it was
the weights for all the different Gaussian and then actually you could see that they're
all zeros because they're all exponent minus 16 so basically they're all zeros and what
found for the coefficient of my polynomial is 0.7 minus 0.15 and 0.35, which are exactly
the values I have. Of course it had no choice to actually find the perfect value for it
because I gave him the perfect point so he had to find the polynomial because I gave him all the
information to find the polynomial and everything else all the Gaussian and all the radial basis
functions are useless for in this case so what I would do is that I would make sure that I actually
have a bit of noise in the data I will give him so it's not a perfect polynomial that I give him
and I don't ask him to solve for perfect polynomial so what I would do is that I would keep the same
axis sample all those axes and then I will make I will offset them to say
well I'm actually I'm not exactly looking at those values it's something a bit
random it's not exactly I've been a bit random here and probably look a bit
weird especially this one we'll see so now I have something a bit
different what I should have is of course my piece that is values I get my standard
and then I will get my weights now I could see that I do have actual weights for my radial basis
functions and I have weights for the polynomial that are not exactly or not at all the polynomial
had at the beginning. And if I do the interpolation, I will get something. That is still a radial
basis function with the added constraint that we kind of know that extrapolation is a polynomial,
a quadratic polynomial. I have a kind of a quadratic polynomial in the middle, so it doesn't
just drop with no reason. It has the polynomial as here and it did its best guess as what the
polynomial and the radial basis functions together should give me as a result for interpolations.
So that's what radial basis functions with extended polynomial is giving you. So I hope
you enjoyed this one and I'll see you next time when we will start to use
radial basis functions in animation papers. See ya!